<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be inquired of in the ordinarie visitation of the right reuerende father in God, William lorde bishop of Couentrie and Lichfielde diligently to be considered of as well by ministers, as churchwardens and swornemen, and aduesedly to be answered particulerly to euerie point, by either of them seuerally in writing, at the visitation to bee holden by the saide reuerend father, or his officers.</title>
            <title>Visitation articles. 1584</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of Lichfield and Coventry. Bishop (1579-1609 : Overton)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00189</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847108</idno>
  <idno type="VID">12120</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240944174</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 10224</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S111845</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99847108e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00189)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12120)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 222:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be inquired of in the ordinarie visitation of the right reuerende father in God, William lorde bishop of Couentrie and Lichfielde diligently to be considered of as well by ministers, as churchwardens and swornemen, and aduesedly to be answered particulerly to euerie point, by either of them seuerally in writing, at the visitation to bee holden by the saide reuerend father, or his officers.</title>
                  <title>Visitation articles. 1584</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of Lichfield and Coventry. Bishop (1579-1609 : Overton)</author>
                  <author>Overton, William, 1525?-1609.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By J. Kingston] for William Brome,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1584]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title (leaf A1 verso) gives date of visitation.</note>
                  <note>Caption title (leaf A4 recto) reads: Certaine aduertisementes, for a continual order to be obserued inuiolably without any alteration touching the pointes following, within the diocesse of Couentrie and Liehfield [sic]. Register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12120:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12120:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Articles to be inquired of in the Ordinarie Visitation of the right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerende Father in GOD, William Lorde Bishop of Couentrie and</hi> Lichfielde, diligently to be conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of as well by Ministers, as Churchwardens and Swornemen, and aduisedly to be answered parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culerly to euerie point, by either of them seuerally in writing, at the Visitation to bée holden by the saide reuerend Father, or his Officers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London for William Brome.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles_of_visitation">
            <pb facs="tcp:12120:2"/>
            <head>Articles to be inquired of in THE ORDINARY VISITA<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>TION OF THE RIGHT REVEREND Father in God, William Lord Bishop of Couentrie and Lichfield, holden Anno 1584, diligently to be considered of, as well by the Ministers, as Church-wardens and sworne men, and aduisedly to be aunswered particularly to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poinct, by eyther of them seuerally in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, at the Visitation holden by the saide reuerende Father or his Officers.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>INprimis,</hi> whether the Church of your Parish be now vacant and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute of an incombent: how long it hath so remained: whether any sequestration be graunted of the Fruits, to whom, and by whom? If it haue an incumbēt, what his name is, of what bringing vp &amp; degrée in Schooles? What the valure of the liuing is in the Quéenes bookes? who is the patrone by right or aduouson? Whether he hath anie mo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, or Ecclesiasticall promotions, how many, and where? If he lie not in his Benefice, to whome he letteth his Tythes, for what yeerely commoditie, the ordinarie charges deducted? Whether the Curate be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and lawfully admitted vpon due trial and examination of his suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie and honestie vnder the Seale of Office?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Whether Common Praier be distinctly and audibly read within the Parishe, and the Sacramentes reuerently and orderly administred and whether for the better performance of thē you haue a booke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon praier, two Psalters, the English Bible, the Homilies, the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrases of <hi>Erasmus</hi> in English, the table of the ten Commandements, a comely Table standing vppon a frame for the holy Communion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently couered, and a conuenient Communion cup, with a couer of sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and a séemelie and decent Pulpit.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> Whether your Altars, Roodeloftes, and other Monumentes of su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition bee cleane defaced and taken away, and whether Masseboo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, Portases, or any superstitious <hi>Legendaries,</hi> Vestiments, Crosses, Images, or any other Reliques or Monuments of Idolatrie, be either knowne or suspected to remaine in any mans handes, and in whose, or what you know are become of those which you had?</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> Whether your Parson, Vicar, or Curate, be a painfull, zelous and diligent preacher: at the least whether he doth procure quarterly or <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nethly
<pb facs="tcp:12120:2"/>Sermons according to the Queenes Iniunctions, especially vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon such daies as the holy Communion shalbe ministred for the better enstruction &amp; preparation towards y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> action: And whether he doth duely and orderly according to the said Iniunctions, Cathechise euery Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day with exposition of the same, for the better instruction of the youth of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> parish, and Christian enformatiō of other the hearers, and whether such as are to be Cathechised attend orderly at the time to be instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or who they be that make default or shew thēselues obstinate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And whether your Minister doth carefully repaire to visite the sick of your Parishe for their spirituall comforte, and willingly attend hys charge in those extremities. And further where hee doth conferre with his Parishioners, especially such as he knoweth not throughly groūded in the way and knowledge of their saluation, for their better instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before they repaire to the holy Communion. And if anye refuse thys necessary conferrence offered by the minister, not only to stay them frō receiuing, but also to present what bee their names with their causes pretended?</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> Whether your Minister doth admit any to the Communion: or to be married, or to answere for Infantes in Babtisme, being not suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently Cathechised and able to yeald an accompt of their christian faith, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whome conscience will not allure almost once to thinke sereously of the meanes of their saluation, yet other extraordinarye occasions maye driue for shame to some knowledge of Christianitie.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> Whether any Officer for fauour, feare, or corruption, hath so qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified or dispensed with any publicke or notorious sinne, that the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders hath bene restored to the Congregation and Sacraments, without christian publicke satisfaction, howe many haue bene presented hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and how their causes haue bene ended, and for what cause the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister without christian publicke satisfaction, hath admitted any to the christian participation of praiers and sacramentes. And whether any Officer, Archedeacon or Officiall haue delt with anye commutation of penaunce, and what bee their names, whose penaunces by them haue bene commuted, for what sinne, and how it hath bene vsed or employed?</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7</hi> Whether your Minister or any other of your Parishe be knowne or suspected as fauourers of the Romish Churche, superioritie, or reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. And whether anye runnagate Iesuites, or counterfaite Massing Priestes, going not according to the order of their professions, are kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen or suspected to frequent or haunt to any person or persons within your Parishe, sometime for a shift to lye or lurke with them: and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they or any Scholemaister, or any other pretending the name of a
<pb facs="tcp:12120:3"/>seruant, are suspected to allure and perswade any within your parishes from the true sinceritie of the Gospell, now by publicke authoritie esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished to the vsing of Mattins, Beades, and suche other vaine Popishe trish trashe: or of any vnlawfull Popish bookes: And whether anye be reputed or suspected to be reconciled to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Church of Rome within your Parish, &amp; what be their names? And whether you know or haue heard of any sometime in orders, that now do liue as lay men?</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8</hi> Whether any of your Parishe doe altogether absent themselues from deuine seruice, or do seldome or negligently come to the Churche, or doe not continue there without disturbance of the Minister and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, not departing thence but vppon some iust and lawfull cause: And whether any of your Parishioners doe not receiue the Communiō at the least thrise in the yeare, according to her Maiesties lawes. And whether any hauing diuers houses of remoue, doe shifte from place to place, in colour to defeate the performance of the Christian ducties in those behalfes, what they be, and the names of euery of the familie that doth the like. And whether the particuler twelue pence be leuied accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Statute?</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9</hi> Whether anye within your parishe, haue anye of their kindred or kinsfolke beyond the Seas, what be their names, and howe long they haue continued out of the realme, and what by hearesay, or in consciēce you iudge ther affection to be in religion: Or whether any are knowne or suspected to relieue any such?</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10</hi> Whether your Minister keep any suspected woman in his house or be geuen to dronkennesse, idlenesse, or be a haunter of. Tauerns, Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houses, or other suspected place, or be Hunters, Hawkers, Dicers, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Tablers, Swearers, or any wayes geue any euill example of life. or vnseemely apparell, to the offence of others, and discredite of their, calling. And whether they be reported or suspected to haue come by their Benefice, or other Ecclesiasticall promotions Simonically, directly, or indirectly?</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11</hi> Whether there belong anye glebe landes to your Parsonage or Vicarage, and how many seuerall parcelles there be, and howe muche they containe by estimation, whether any be alienated, exchaunged, or encroched vpon to the decay of the liuing? And whether your Chansell and Parsonage houses be in good and sufficient reparations, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your Church be in euery parte so maintained as were csnuenient. And whether your Churchyardes be throughly fenced about and clenly kept, and who is the cause of anye of these defaultes. And whether any Patrones haue decayed the Parsonage houses, and keep a Stipend <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12120:3"/>Priest in place, where an Incumbent should be possessed?</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12</hi> Whether your Minister keepe well their Registers of all Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, Burialles, and Christninges within your Parish, according to the Quéenes Iniunctions, and doe present a Copie of them once euery yeare by Indenture, to the Chauncellor or his Deputie, to remaine of recorde in the principall Office.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13</hi> Whether any within your Parish administer the goods of those that bee dead without lawfull authoritie: Or any are suspected to haue suppressed or altered the last wil of the dead, or any Executors that haue not fulfilled the Testators will, especially in performing of Legacies geuen to other good vses, or maintenaunce of the poore.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14</hi> Whether you haue a Schoolemaister in your Parishe, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your Schoolemaister teaching publickely or priuately bee of good and sincere religion &amp; conuersation, and whether they be examined and allowed by the Ordenarie or his Officer in that behalfe. And whether any liuing giuen towardes the erection or maintenaunce of any schoole, be withholden backe or otherwise any waies employed.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15</hi> Whether any haue pulled down or discouered any church, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell or Chappell, Porche, Vestrie, Steeple, Almehouse, Belles, or anye parte of them, or felled Wood or Timber in the churchyarde. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your Hospitalles, Spittelles, or Almeshouses be well and godly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and maintained according to the foundation and auncient ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the same?</p>
            <p n="16">
               <hi>16</hi> Whether any entertainment bee geuen, or gaming vsed in anye Innes or Alehouses, or other Victualers in time of deuine Seruice or Sermons: Or whether any Butchers, Victualers, Pedlers, or anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Artificers in time of common prayer or Sermon, open their shops or wares: And whether your Minister customably remembreth your Churchwardens and Swornemen, to attend their charge in suche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe.</p>
            <p n="17">
               <hi>17</hi> Whether your church goods, stockes, or rentes be let to the best commoditie, and for such vses as they were first ment, or now are to be employed and conuerted, no other waies. Or whether the same bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased or decayed, by what meanes, who being churchwardens, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any are behinde with making their accomptes, or be thought not to haue made a true, perfect, and sufficient accompt, what landes or stocks should be or yet remaine?</p>
            <p n="18">
               <hi>18</hi> Whether any within your Parishe be suspected to vse Sorcerie, Witchcraft, Charmes, vnlawful Prayers, or Inuocations in Latin or English: namely, Midwiues in time of womens trauaile with childe:
<pb facs="tcp:12120:4"/>and who resorte to such for helpe or counsaile?</p>
            <p n="19">
               <hi>19</hi> Whether the Minister or Churchwardens haue suffered anye Lordes of Misrule, or Sommer Lords or Ladies, or any disguised per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, or Morisedancers, or others at Christmas, or any time in sommer to come vnreuerently pyping, dauncing, or playing in church or church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde, with vnseemely scoffes, iestes, ribauldrie, or at any other place &amp; time, namely in time of deuine Seruice, or Sermons, and what they be that commit such disorders, or accompanie, or maintaine them?</p>
            <p n="20">
               <hi>20</hi> Whether any of your parish haue bene maried within y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> degrees of affinitie, and consanguinitie forbidden by the lawes of God, &amp; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the better knowledge and direction of those degrees, you haue the Table drawne out to that ende, affixed publiquely in your Parishe Churche: And whether any diuorsed or separated for marying within those degrees, be notwithstanding conuersant and keep company toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Whether any man be suspected to haue two wiues, anye woman two husbandes, any maried after a former precontract: any priuy or se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret contractes without consent of Parentes, Tutors, or Gouernors: or any married without Banes thrise solemply asked: or out of your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish where one of them at the least doth inhabite. And whether any mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ried liue apart, and not continue together according to the lawes of god and the realme. What licences so marry haue bene graunted since the death of the last Bishop, the Ministers shall exhibite to vs or our Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers at the Visitation.</p>
            <p n="21">
               <hi>21</hi> Whether any of your Parish be known, defamed, or vehemently suspected of any notorious sinne, fault, or crime, as of Vserie, swearing Adulterie, Fornication, Incest, Baudrie, Drunkennesse, Ribaldrie, Slaundering, Contention, sowing of discorde betweene neighbours, priuie receiuing women vnlawfully begotten with childe, or suffering them to depart before publicke satisfaction made to the Congregatign? Or whether there be any fightersr Quarrellers, Brawlers, or Chiders in the Churche or Churchyarde, anye Scoffers, Rimers, or diriders of Ministers, or any that lay violent handes on them, or any of them, or otherwise abuse them?</p>
            <p>All and euery of the particulers of the premises you are dilligently to enquire of, and as well the ministers seuerally, as the Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and Sidemen, ioyntly to present the defaultes of euery of them in writing subscribed with their names. And generally whatsoeuer brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and offences els they shall know or heare committed against anye of the Queenes Maiesties Iniunctions, or anye of the Ecclesiasticall Lawes of this Realme.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb facs="tcp:12120:4"/>
            <head>Certaine aduertisementes, FOR A CONTINVAL ORDER TO BE obserued inuiolably without any alteration touching the pointes following, within the Diocesse of Couentrie and Liehfield.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>INprimis,</hi> for that the want of a sufficient Ministerie is not onely the Nurse of Ignorance and Popery, but also the cause of all Atheisme, disobedience, and dissolutenesse of life: And the corruptiō of Patrons, aboundeth to the great decay of the sufficient maintenance of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, this setled order is set down to preuent either inconueniece wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of all Patrones together with such as are to be presented to Benifices, hereby without further intimation are to take knowledge within this Diocease of Couentrie and Lichfield, <hi>vz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That whosoeuer shall hereafter bee presented to any Benifice, shall attend for his publicke examination the first day of euerie moneth only, openly in the consistorie at Lichfield, betwéene the houres of eight and aleuen (if it be not a Sonday or Holiday) then the next daie following, where the reuerende Father in God the now Lord Bishop in person, or the Chauncellor at the least, or the Chauncelors Deputie giuing atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and calling for their assistance foure other Preachers at the least shall and will cause the gifts and learning of the partie presented to bee throughly examined, and presently vppon conference betwene them of his sufficiencie, to set their Iudgementes downe solempnly in a booke made and kept for that purpose, to notifie their allowance, or dissallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wance. And for the better and more assured performannce of this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertisement greatly heretofore neglected and abused, as well for want of appointing certaine sufficient and sincere Examiners vsually to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this charge as otherwise, the said reuerend Father in his now pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>posed Visitation will publish to the whole Countrey the names of such Preachers, by whose credite and conscience he will chiefly commit this charge and trust, besides the pretence of such as being alwaies néere at hande may be vsed and required.</p>
            <p>And although the man for his learning shall be quallified, and bring besides Letters testimoniall for his good behauiour according to order, yet for that such Testimonialls haue by often and too much experience béene proued to procéed or hearesay, and importunitie of intreatie, with out any through knowledge of the partie so commended. Therefore the
<pb facs="tcp:12120:5"/>partie so presented and allowed as before, shall with license of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie, repaire eftsons to that Parish, and aswell acquaint his Parish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with his persone as his giftes, that moneth onely, reading the first Sunday he commeth thither, this publicke aduertisement in time of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Seruice. And so the first day of the next moneth following, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire to the saide reuerend Father, or by his direction to the Office for his Institution, (if none shall vndertake to proue against him some notorious default that day of his apparance) and so without further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay to bee dispatched, giuing first his oath besides other matters, that neither by himselfe, nor any for him he hath vsed Simonie, in attaining to that liuing directly or indirectly, according to the Ecclesiastical laws in that behalfe prouided and established.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Item, for that the lawes of this Realme do permit diuers persons sufficiently qualified and dispensed withall, to enioye twoo Benefices, and to demise the one to a sufficient Curate, it is likewise ordered that the first day of the next moneth after the Visitation ended, all the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, in, &amp; throughout the Diocesse of Couentrie and Lichfield, shal at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend at the Consistorie Court, where the foresaide reuerend Father in person, or his Chauncelor at the least, or the Chancelors deputy assisted with foure preachers, named &amp; published in euerie sessiō of this visitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with other such neere assistants, as shalbe called and vsed as before, wil be readie to sit for that purpose, and exhibiting their former licenses to the Ordinarie, if so be vpon this further triall and examination, they shall appeare méete in all respects for that congregation, euerie circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance well waied &amp; duly considered then to be continued in the former place and seruice, otherwise to haue warning to depart, and the Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent likewise to haue conuenient notice to prouide him of a more suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Minister within a reasonable time: And no Curate to be accepted or allowed in any Parishe without the license of the Ordinarie vnder his seale. Prouided further, that the licenses graunted to Curates shall not generally extend to any place vncertainely, but shall namely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the particular Parish whereto he shall be commended, and that al licenses contrarie to this order to be reformed. And further that no Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, who are to supplye the absence of an other qualified by lawe, bee vsed as instruments onely by colour to defeat the good meaning of the Statutes in that behalfe prouided, to the benefit of Laie men, but them selues to enioy the commodities allotted to their owne better mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naner, according to the true meaning of the Statute.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> Item, for that the peruerse obstinate vntowardnesse of diuers yong Gentlemen in religion, doth argue a manifest &amp; most intollerable cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
<pb facs="tcp:12120:5"/>in their bringing vp and in Schoolemaisters, that all Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maisters, aswel in anie noble or Gentlemens houses, as otherwise pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly or priuately teaching within anie Towne of this Diocesse, shall likewise bring in their Licences heretofore to them graunted, the third daie of the first moneth next after the Visitation before the saide reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father, or his Chauncelor at the least, or the Chauncelors Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, with the foresaide Preachers and assistantes attending this seruice in the Consistorie at Lichfielde, to whom if they do not sufficiently al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their habilitie for learning, their soundnesse for Religion, their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestie for connersation by learning and testimonie of suche as are well knowne to the Bishop, then to bee displaced and inhibited to continue their teaching anie longer within this Diocease Otherwise with very good fauour and allowance to remaine in their former estate, enioined once a quarter at the least to examine his schollers in the Catechisme, and to sée them frequent al exercises of Religion according to their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion: And no Schoolemaister to haue or enioy any generall Licence, throughout the whole Diocease vncertainely, but to teach in that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer place whereto he shall bee allowed, and the Licences contrarie to this order to be reformed.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> Item, for that to helpe the lamentable inconueniences growing to the Church of God by the insufficient Ministerie, they are not onely to be sifted which are already made Ministers, but also a diligent care and foresight is to be vsed, that only sufficient men be admitted to that func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereafter. Therefore the foresaide reuerend Father would haue al and euery within this Diocease of Couentrie and Lichfield, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for themselues or their frendes, to sollicite for orders of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie to take knowledge hereby, that they &amp; euery of them must attend for publike examination and triall, the first day of euerie quarter of the yéere, onely in the Comistorie of Lichfielde, where the said reuerend, or his Chauncelor with the Archdeacons and other assistances and forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Preachers to be called, making due proofe by publicke examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all circumstances required by law, and immediatly setting down their iudgements accordingly, and if he or they vpon such triall shall be found worthy, then by the said reuerend Father to receiue orders, if the said reuerend Father shall thinke it so méete and conuenient, otherwise either to be cleane reiected, or referred ouer to their further sufficiencie: and no prinate orders otherwise either to be sued, looked for, or perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med within this Diocease of Couentrie and Lichfield.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> Item, for that sundrie and manifolde inconueniences haue ensued the graunt of Licenses to marrie, these circumstances shal be obserued,
<pb facs="tcp:12120:6"/>by the Officers who are to graunt the same. First, that they do not rash<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly without aduertisement frō the Minister, or some such as they know to be of good credit and honestie graunt the License. Secondly, that they include in the bands taken consent of the Parents, Tutors, or Couer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors. Thirdly, that the direction of the license be made to one of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, where the parties to be maried shall dwell, who cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant of the estate of the parties, and may stay the procéeding to mariage according to the License, if he know or suspect any lawful impediment, aduertising the Chauncelor with all conuenient speed of the cause of his stay Other wese no License to be graunted, vnlesse the matter be noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously knowne to the Officer authorised to dispence in that behalfe.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> Item, that none denounced or to be denounced and published excom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>municate, shall hereafter be admitted to the Church, or receiuing of the Sacramenis, without his absolution testified to the Minister &amp; Church wardens, vnder the Ordinaries hand or Seale: And that such as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue obstinatly so denounced or excommunicate, be publikely notified to the whole Congregation from time to time to their amendment or further discredite.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7</hi> Item that the ordinance of the Booke of Common Praier bee from henceforth obserued in this, that the Bread deliuered to the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants, be such as is vsual to be eaten at the Table with other meals, yet of the purest and finest Wheat: and no other bread to be vsed by the Minister, nor to be prouided for by the Churchwardens &amp; Parishners then such finest common bread.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8</hi> Item, whereas priuate Baptisme in time of necessitie séemeth tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated by the Booke of Common Praier, and therevpon not onely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners old women and Midwiues haue hoth against Gods laws and the meaning of the said Booke, presumed to intrude themselues into that ministerie &amp; function, but also vnder cullor of such priuate Baptismes, many times wicked Iesuits, masse Priests or Reconcilers haue béene knowne to Baptise Infants: It is therefore ordered to be receiued and obserued, that if vpon any reasonable causes mouing the Parents and Minister, they thinke not good to expect the next Sabaoth or Holyday, for the more commendable performance of that Sacrament in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of the whole Congregation at Church: That then it be performed with a conuenient multitude of such as shalbe knowne sound and well effected to Religion, and either by the Minister of the Parish himselfe, or other knowne Minister with his priuitie or consent. And that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth no women presume to intrude themselues into Babtizing of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants in any respect or condition.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb facs="tcp:12120:6"/>
               <hi>9</hi> Item, for the better obseruing of all and singuler these aduertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and due presentment of the seuerall breaches and defaults of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same and the foresaid Articles, it is ordered that speciall choyse and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde be made of such Churchwardens and Sidemen in euery Parishe, Village and Humlet, whiche are knowne to fauour and conforme them selues to the lawes and Religion nowe established, and be of honest and good accompt for their life and maners, and not towardes such as bee professed &amp; obstinate Recusantes, and that according to the wholesome aduertisementes and Canons in that behalfe prouided, no elections be made of the foresaid Officers in the Ministers absence or without hys consent. And that euery Minister shall haue a speciall care and regarde of his duetie in this behalfe vpon his credite w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his Ordinary, as wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon dependeth the whole direction of reformation of things amisse.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10</hi> Item, whereas the foresaid Officers stande charged by vertue of their corporall othes taken faithfully and carefully to discharge their dueties, and without fauoure; malice, or feare, truely to present all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults &amp; abuses as they fall out from time to time, aswell for the auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of wilfull periurie, as the preuenting and cutting off of sinne &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences before they grow to full &amp; perfect ripenesse, the Minister shall do well euery sonday &amp; holiday after euening prayer to call the Churche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens and Sidemen of euery Parishe vnto him in the Churche, and there to conferre and aduise together vppon perusall and consideration of these articles and aduertisementes, what hath fallen out within that their Parish contrarie to any of them worthy reformation or present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or worthy priuate admonition for amendment: And so eyther ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their discretions to admonish the parties to preuēt their own discredites, and any publicke offence like to growe: or els to present or notifie all suche euill misdemeanours to the Chancellour, or such Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missaries, Deane, Rurales, or other Officers, as hée shall thinke best to appoint in euerie Deanrie from time to time.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11</hi> Item, that euery Minister within this Diocease bring in and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite to the Chauncellour at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Visitation, his letters of orders, his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters dismisories if he came out of an other Diocease, his Institutiō, his Qualification, and dispensation to remaine in recorde in the Office.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12</hi> Item, for that some offences and greuaunces haue alreadie and may grow hereafter to the subiect, by taking or exacting excessiue fees contrarie to law &amp; the vsuall custome of this Diocease, to the misliking and discredite of Ecclesiasticall iurisdiction and the Officers thereof, &amp; therefore the Ordinarie to preuent all inconueniences in that behalfe, hath geuen order, that as well his Chauncellor and Commissarie from
<pb facs="tcp:12120:7"/>time to time, as his Register shall haue a Table in either of their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces openly and publickely hanged vp to be seene, read, &amp; considered of by euery one that shall be disposed or occasioned so to doe: wherein shall be fairely written and contained the seuerall rates of all and singuler sées due and appertaining to either of their Offices, and euery particulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by them or either of them to be dispatched: whereby the sueters can not or neede not to be abused: yet for that some of simplicitie may be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner-reached, and either for their daily labours whereby they liue are not able, or for feare of charges with delay woulde bee loth to prosecute reformation to their restitution. It hath further pleased the Lorde Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop to prouide further in that behalfe, that euery Minister hearing any such griefe of any his Parishners, may be bold by his Letters onely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the Chauncellour, to certifie him of any such complaynt, with all the truth and circumstance of their dealing, and that by the Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour the fault be presently looked into and reformed, whether it concerneth himselfe or the Register, without anye further charges or adoe, as they will haue the good fauour and liking of the Bishoppe, and aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere vppon their perill to the contrary.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12120:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>